RYAN MCMICHAEL

Production Manager / Software Developer

(770) 539-1463 LinkedIn.com/in/ryancmcmichael Ryancmcmichael.github.io

Ryancmcmichael@gmail.com

Production Manager with software development schooling and experience. Combining a wide variety of skills and exposure to bring a unique and capable aspect to any team. Experience wearing many different hats and adapting to circumstances to ensure that the job gets done.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

PRODUCTION MANAGER

Cabinets by Design, Duluth, GA, October 2013 - Present

Originally hired as a Junior Estimator, worked intermittently while finishing college coursework, promoted rapidly through multiple production-related roles based upon aptitude, learning ability, and leadership ability. Currently oversee over 60 production employees to ensure production does not halt.

- ~ Improved overall production by a sustained near 10% margin.
- Decreased turnover rate by 15% by improving training, safety standards, and recruiting methods.
- Reduced overtime costs 10% annually by more effectively scheduling production to meet project deadlines.
- ~ Implemented and maintain Seradex, a custom-configured ERP software.
- ~ Create, test, and deploy custom tools to integrate within the ERP system.
- Saved time in estimating process by creating custom tools to minimize manual input and data processing.
- ~ Drive production by tracking project status through project managers, business owner, and engineering manager.
- Coordinate and conduct meetings to ensure product arrives on schedule.
- Improved employee morale by regularly meeting with employees to talk about and understand problems each person is facing while developing solutions to those problems.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

WhatsThe.Buzz, Marietta, GA, January 2017 - May 2017

Hired to improve several features of an existing service, from overall user interface to the ways in which data is presented to clients.

- ~ Increased subscriptions by 10% in period immediately following release of new improvements.
- Site traffic increased over 50% in the month following release, indicating a tremendous improvement in product usefulness.
- Improved data gathering techniques to garner more valuable data to be passed back to the client.
- Leveraged Javascript graphing libraries to display collected data in a concise, understandable manner.
- Combined use of PHP and Javascript to update and maintain data in MySQL database.
- Used Twitter's Bootstrap framework to enable both web users and mobile users to access the system.
- Learned techniques of agile project management and rapid prototyping to maximize value of time spent with product owner.
- ~ Developed automated testing tools to ensure a consistent and stable user experience.

PROGRAM SPECIALIST

Pay It Forward Scholarships, Gainesville, GA, June 2012 - September 2013

Hired to maintain records and disseminate scholarships, quickly promoted to managing program so that company owner could invest time in soliciting donations. Trained and managed staff to ensure highest standards of customer experience.

- Maintained accurate records for large nonprofit. These records were for donations received and scholarships granted; these were updated to reflect changes in personal accounts.
- ~ Created weekly, monthly, and yearly summary and audit reports using Microsoft Excel.

REFERENCES

Available upon request.

Skills

Agile Development
Programming Languages:

- ~ Java
- ~ C++
- ~ PHP
- ~ HTML
- JavaScript
- ~ CSS
- ~ C
- ~ Ada
- ~ Python
- ~ VBA

Databases:

- Microsoft SQL
- ~ OpenSQL
- ~ MySQL

Project Management
Production Management and
Scheduling

Enterprise Resource Planning Inventory Management Employee Hiring and Training

Education

Bachelor of Science

Computer Science, 3.87/4.00 GPA Kennesaw State University

Associate of Science

Engineering, 3.66/4.00 GPA University of North Georgia

Accomplishments

Managed production in excess of \$20 million over 6 months, the most productive period in company history

Decreased annual turnover rate to **below 15%**, the lowest in company history

Hired and trained more than 20 new employees

Financial responsibility for over \$12 million annually